Inventory of the Sir Paul Dukes papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Sir Paul Dukes papers
1915-1990
89082
Dukes, Paul, Sir, 1889-1967.
4 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (1.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Diaries, writings, lectures, notes, letters, clippings, memorabilia, and photographs relating to British intelligence operations, especially during the Russian Revolution, to popularization of Yoga in the Western world, and to personal affairs. Includes fictional writings, poems and musical compositions. Also includes some material relating to Sir Paul Dukes collected by Robin Bruce Lockhart.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1989.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Sir Robert Hamilton Bruce Lockhart papers, Hoover Institution Archives.
Scope and Content of Collection
Diaries, writings, lectures, notes, letters, clippings, memorabilia, and photographs relating to British intelligence operations, especially during the Russian Revolution, to popularization of Yoga in the Western world, and to personal affairs. Includes fictional writings, poems and musical compositions. Also includes some material relating to Sir Paul Dukes collected by Robin Bruce Lockhart.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Espionage, British--Soviet Union.; Secret service--Great Britain.; Yoga.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Lockhart, Robin Bruce.
Collection Contents
- Personal profile complied by Robin Bruce Lockhart, 1915-1990 (Box 1)
  Includes award certificates; biographical note; correspondence; notes; and photographic prints and negatives.
- Personal documents, 1915-1965 (Box 1)
  Includes correspondence with the Dalai Lama and Pandit Nehru; genealogical essay on the Dukes family; maps; passports; and photographic prints.
- Miscellaneous documents, 1937-1990 (Box 1)
  Includes articles by Paul Dukes; certificate of registration; correspondence; list of contents; marriage certificate; notes; proposals; and writing fragments.
- Clippings, official documents issued by Soviet authorities, and photographic prints, 1917-1968 (Box 1)
- Short stories by Paul Dukes, 1925-1965 (Box 2)
- Musical compositions, 1950-1965 (Box 2)
  Includes clipping, card, poem, scores, scripts, and sheet music.
- Poems, 1950-1960 (Box 2)
- Clippings, largely relating to the espionage activities of Paul Dukes, 1951-1965 (Box 2)
- "Sai Baba," manuscript by Paul Dukes relating to his travels in India, 1963 (Box 2)
  Includes letter.
- Published articles by Paul Dukes on the practice of yoga, 1949-1961 (Box 2)
- Lectures and other writings by Paul Dukes, largely relating to the practice of yoga, 1950-1957 (Box 2)
- Clippings, largely relating to the teaching of yoga by Paul Dukes and Diana Fitzgerald, 1958-1964 (Box 2)
- Photographic prints, largely depicting Paul Dukes and Diana Fitzgerald engaged in yoga activities, 1955-1965 (Box 3)
- Album of photographs depicting scenes in India, including some portraying Paul Dukes, 1950 (Box 4)
- Diaries, 1918-1922, 1926-1927, 1932, 1935-1936, 1940, 1942, 1946, 1956-1958 (Box 5)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes notes and list of contents compiled by Robin Bruce Lockhart, 1990.